Finding aid for the David Bernstein papers LSC.2126
UCLA Library Special Collections
David Bernstein papers
1964-1997
UCLA Library Special Collections
Bernstein, David L.
LSC.2126
10.4 linear feet (24 boxes and 1 carton)
From 1979 to 1997, David Bernstein served as investigator and legal researcher for the Elmer "Geronimo" Pratt defense team. The collection consists of research, numerous court documents, transcripts, and Freedom of Information materials that were accrued during the various court hearings. The bulk of the materials are facsimiles of original documents.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of David Bernstein, 2012.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9974964793606533
Biography/History
David L. Bernstein was born in Atlanta, Georgia, on January 26, 1948; he moved to Los Angeles at a young age. He graduated from the University of California at Berkeley in 1971 and earned a JD from the University of La Verne College of Law in 1995. After working for several years with environmental cleanup in Northern California, he returned to Los Angeles in the late 1970's and took a job as law clerk/investigator in the Law Offices of Goldin and Gordon. One of the partners, Martha Goldin, had served as appellate counsel for former Black Panther Elmer Geronimo Pratt. In 1979 Bernstein was assigned to review and index criminal appellate briefs and learned that there were ongoing habeas corpus proceedings seeking to overturn Pratt's murder conviction, as well as litigation under the Freedom of Information Act to ascertain if the FBI's Counter Intelligence Program had any role in the conviction. With the approval from Goldin and Gordon, Bernstein contacted Pratt's main counsel, Stuart Hanlon and offered to join the efforts being made on Pratt's behalf.
From 1979 to 1997, Bernstein served as investigator and legal researcher for the Pratt defense team. In May of 1997, Pratt's conviction was overturned and he was released after serving nearly 27 years in prison.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of files amassed by lawyer David L. Bernstein documenting his involvement pertaining to the court case of People v. Pratt (former Black Panther Leader Elmer "Geronimo" Pratt) and proceedings seeking to overturn Pratt's murder conviction, as well as litigation to ascertain if the FBI's Counter Intelligence Program had any role in the conviction. Includes research, numerous court documents, transcripts, and Freedom of Information materials that were accrued during the various court hearings. The bulk of the materials are facsimiles of original documents.
Organization and Arrangement
The collection is arranged in a loose chronological order.
Pratt, Elmer Geronimo -- Trials, litigation, etc.; Bernstein, David L.
- FBI summaries of Louise Manaco, Annette Becker, Christi Farlice, and Ronald Freeman, no dates (Box 15)
- Counter intelligence: FBI and other documents binder (in 3 folders), 1964-1987 (Box 5)
- Julius Butler FBI documents binder, 1967-1970 (Box 12)
- Tyrone binder (Tyrone Hutchinson and Tyrone LaVerne Bass), 1967-1971 (Box 21)
- FBI Black Panther Party binder, 1968 (Box 15)
- Pratt case exhibits, memorandum, and correspondence, 1968,1971,1972,1981 (Box 15)
- Pratt and related matters newspaper coverage binder (in 3 folders), 1968-1996 (Box 8)
- Congressional hearings and reports Black Panther Party (in 2 folders), 1969 (Box 10)
- David Bernstein memos to Julius Butler binder, 1969-1980 (Box 12)
- FBI documents binder (in 3 folders), 1969 (Box 18)
- FBI electronic surveillance logs (in 2 folders), 1969 Mar-Sep (Box 6)
- FBI electronic surveillance logs of the Black Panther Party binder (in 2 folders), 1969 Oct-Dec (Box 24)
  General
  Electronic surveillance logs of Black Panther Party in Los Angeles and Oakland, California.
- Mary Fischer (GQ reporter) return of materials borrowed from Bernstein, 1969-1972; 1996 (Box 18)
- Melvin (Cotton) Smith FBI reports, testimony, and federal documents binder (in 2 folders), 1969 (Box 7)
- United States v. Freed Sutherland binder, 1969 (Box 19)
- Roger (Blue) Lewis witness file binder, 1969-1985 (Box 10)
- 1969 Shootout preliminary hearing - Reporter's Transcript of LAPD testimony, 1970 (Box 12)
- FBI documents binder (in 2 folders), 1970 (Box 20)
- People v. Bryan shootout trial binder (folder 1 of 2), 1970s (Box 17)
- People v. Bryan shootout trial binder (folder 2 of 2), 1970s (Box 18)
- Tennis Court Murder proceedings (grand jury and pretrial motions) binder, 1970-1972 (Box 19)
- FBI documents binder (in 2 folders), 1971 (Box 20)
- David Bernstein research binder, 1971-1979 (Box 19)
  Binder originally labeled Miscellaneous docs re. anything and everything.
  This is truly a miscellaneous.
  Unorganized mixture of various information related to Pratt case.
- David Bernstein general investigation (witnesses and important personages) binder (in 2 folders), 1971-1981 (Box 24)
- Habeas corpus DA filing, witness list, and Tennis Court Trial summaries of witness testimony, 1972, 1996 (Box 7)
- Tennis Court Trial - Kalustian's notes, 1972 (Box 23)
- Reporter's Transcript of Tennis Court Trial - defense and rebuttal witnesses, deliberation, new trial motion, and sentencing binder (folder 1 of 2), 1972 (Box 10)
- Reporter's Transcript of Tennis Court Trial - defense and rebuttal witnesses, deliberation, new trial motion, and sentencing binder (folder 2 of 2), 1972 (Box 11)
- Pratt FBI documents binder, 1972-1973 (Box 7)
- Greg Goldin's files (Reporter), ca. 1973 (Box 3)
  General note
  Original Pratt Opening Brief on appeal from tennis court trial conviction, filed 1973.
- FBI Prison Suit Discovery binder, 1974-1980 (Box 19)
- FBI teletype regarding the stabbing of a prison guard, 1975 Jan 28 (Box 15)
- Los Angeles Police Department binder, 1975-1980 (Box 12)
  Binder labeled Los Angeles Police Department; II. McClellan Hearings (June 24, 1969); IV. Media & Miscellaneous. Inventory lists as Misc. Docs. re. LAPD-CCS. We believe CCS is an acronym for Criminal Conspiracy Section.
  Photocopies of articles and documents.
- Reporter's Transcript of Tennis Court Trial - prosecution witness binder (folder 1 of 2), ca. 1975 (Box 8)
- Reporter's Transcript of Tennis Court Trial - prosecution witness binder (folder 2 of 2), ca. 1975 (Box 9)
- Deposition of Richard Wallace Held in Fonda v. Grey lawsuit, 1976 Dec 20 (Box 13)
- Daniel Bernstein general investigation files, 1979, 1983 (Box 4, Box 5)
- Habeas corpus - proceedings, transcripts, and media binder, 1979 (Box 24)
- Habeas corpus - District Attorney's return to petition binder, 1979 (Box 23)
- Pratt habeas corpus, 1979 (Box 13)
- Pratt habeas corpus - exhibits in support of petition, 1979 (Box 14)
- David Bernstein general investigation binder (in 2 folders), 1980 (Box 16)
- Habeas corpus - Amici Curiae brief, 1980 (Box 14)
- Habeas in California Court of Appeals - documents and David Bernstein research binder (in 2 folders), 1980 (Box 9)
- Habeas corpus - court's opinion, 1980 (Box 15)
  In Re. Pratt; 112 Cal.App.3d 795.
- Habeas corpus - Pratt's supplemental submissions, 1980 (Box 13)
- Habeas corpus - summary of interviews of FBI agents, 1980 (Box 15)
- FBI documents (released through the Freedom of Information Act) binder (in 2 folders), 1980 (Box 17)
- Tennis Court Trial - petitions for review to California Supreme Court, 1980-1996 (Box 13)
- Amnesty International publications, 1981 (Box 13)
- David Bernstein on Roger Aldee radio program - transcript, 1981 Mar 31 (Box 13)
- David Bernstein general investigation binder (in 2 folders), 1981 (Box 17)
- Federal Habeas corpus - documents requested from FBI, 1981 (Box 14)
- Federal habeas corpus - Swearingen and Mahoney (1 of 5 volumes of witness testimony), 1981, 1985 (Box 15)
- Federal habeas corpus - Mahoney, Alexander, Gardner, and Callahan (2 of 5 volumes of witness testimony), 1981, 1985 (Box 15)
- Federal habeas corpus - Held (3 of 5 volumes of witness testimony), 1981, 1985 (Box 16)
- Federal habeas corpus - Held, Bloeser, and Cleary testimony (4 of 5 volumes of witness testimony), 1981, 1985 (Box 16)
- Federal habeas corpus - closing arguments (5 of 5 volumes of witness testimony), 1981, 1985 (Box 16)
- Federal habeas corpus - Pratt V. McCarthy pleading and correspondence binder (in 2 folders), 1981 (Box 6)
- Pratt v. McCarthy opinion by Judge Wallace in Daily Appellate Report, 1981 Jul 1 (Box 15)
- David Bernstein general investigation binder, 1982 (Box 12)
- David Bernstein and Johnathan Lubell correspondence binder, 1982 (Box 6)
- David Bernstein general investigation binder (in 2 folders), 1984 (Box 11)
- David Bernstein general investigation binder (folder 1 of 2), 1985-1991 (Box 7)
- David Bernstein general investigation binder (folder 2 of 2), 1985-1991 (Box 8)
- Last Black Panther (The) by Peter Ransley - unproduced screenplay, 1986 (Box 15)
- Habeas corpus - exhibits in support of petition, 1991 (Box 14)
- Centurion Ministries investigation and report binder, 1993 (Box 11)
- Centurion Ministries report to Los Angeles District Attorney's Office binder, 1993 (Box 22)
- Elmer G. Pratt - petition for writ of habeas corpus, 1996 (Box 13)
- Habeas corpus - District Attorney interview of Roger Lewis, 1996 (Box 13)
- Habeas corpus - District Attorney's interview with Melvin (Cotton) Smith, 1996 (Box 12)
- Habeas corpus - District Attorney interviews, memorandum, and faxes, 1996 (Box 13)
- Habeas corpus - discovery from Los Angeles District Attorney binder (in 2 folders), 1996 (Box 9)
- Habeas corpus - partial reporter's transcript, 1996 Jul 15 (Box 15)
- Habeas corpus - Pratt Attorney's hand written notes regarding witness testimony (7 spiral notepads), 1996 (Box 23)
- Habeas corpus - reporter's transcripts of witness testimony binder, 1996 (Box 22)
- Habeas corpus - reporter's transcripts of witness testimony binder, 1996 (Box 23)
- Habeas corpus - Reporter's Transcript (in Box 1), testimony and some exhibits, 1996-1997 (Box 1, Box 2)
  Scope and Content
  Habeas corpus Reporter's Transcript (in Box 1), testimony and some exhibits
- Tennis Court Trial - Kalustian's trial notebook, 1996 (Box 23)
- Email from Goldin to Bernstein, 1997 (Box 13)
- In Re: Elmer Gerard Pratt - LA Weekly article by Greg Goldin - first draft, 1997 (Box 12)
- Black Panther Party surveillance binder, 1970-1971 (Box 25)
  Scope and Contents
  Box also contains petition for Habeas Corpus and related documents (1984-1997).